i was reading that suitor
of talapute he's saying
he's saying
how he wanted to live when will i live
in the forest he's fantasizing
and enjoying romanticizing about the
mossy mossy rocks and yeah when will i hear
mossy rocks and yeah when will i hear
the then when he was there
the mind wants to go back to life and
then he says no he won't
exist so he starts to say when will i
be a great monk when will i be at peace
and then he starts to tell off his mind
ask the mind questions like why
didn't you didn't you urge me on before
yeah become an ascetic
go to the forest and yet now you want
me to go after the things that you said
i should be giving up
well i've given them up and so
i'm not going to go and do those things
which i
vomited up i'm not going to eat it again
and then he continues to berate the mind
in such a way like
and that and at the end starts to say
well now i'm in control yeah i'm going to tie
now i'm in control yeah i'm going to tie
you down
until you sort of get tamed yeah well
that's that's
that is everyone's relationship with
their own mind usually well not usually
always the only difference is how much
the only difference is how much
perspective in regards to what you have
or uh how much you identify with it the
mind presents you these ideas
and then you accept them and then you
act out of them and then you kind of
assume the ownership of them
but you didn't really have say in in
their in their creation in their arising
the mind came up with it and then oh
yeah i have these thoughts but then you
lose also it's not about me coming up with it
also it's not about me coming up with it
or me
owning or disowning that which is not in
my control
up to me is basically whether i choose
to accept it
what the mind presented me with in the
same sense whether you choose to accept
what the eyes want to see
eyes are pulling in a direction but you
don't have to accept it
you don't have to go with it but
if people have no self-awareness no
perspective developed through sense
restraint for them that pull is theirs ironically
for them that pull is theirs ironically
like they're being pulled
against their will but they believe
that's what they want to do
but obviously uh teleport in that had
had already some wisdom there because he
already was able to see a mind as this
thing that oh yeah you urge me to do this i
that oh yeah you urge me to do this i
did this
now you want to go back if he didn't
have wisdom he would have just thought i
want to go back
but he questioned well is this what i
want oh this is what my mind wants
it's clear enough but is this what i
want
and no i don't want to eat what i
vomited and i was miserable over there
that's why i left
to try this so i don't want to do it
but the mind still wants it so there's a
conflict so you have a choice give in to
the mind
in order to not endure the conflict or
tame the mind
in order to resolve the conflict because
there will be no more conflict
when you are in charge but that's the
mind offered him something good exactly
offered him something good exactly
exactly yeah yeah he was and obviously
that was due to you know his own
pondering reflection choices
he he did meet the buddha as well um so
then he thought actually
even his own mind thought this is worth
while doing like even his own mind was
not happy in that environment
which is why i presented him with his
with his romantic ideas of the forest
uh in the jungle but then when the you
know the reality
of those romantic ideas sets in the
hardship and during the elements of the
insects then the mind changed itself
oh actually i wanna i changed my mind i
want to go back
my mind has changed he wants to go back
but shall i follow it no that's like what
shall i follow it no that's like what
we're saying
you start seeing yourself as this
creature the five sixth sense animal
that senses will operate for as long as
you live they will want to pull you in
direction they want to go
but it's you to stop gratuitously
identifying with them and giving in to
their pressure
and then they'll obey eventually how
long that would take
is how much effort you put in here and
the chief
is the mind that's the dead animal which
exactly the mind directs all the other animals
the mind directs all the other animals
and the mind is basically that which is
the hardest to tame
but it's still the same principle so you
recognize you have such and such
thoughts but then you you reflect further like
but then you you reflect further like
the mind like when the mind is sort of
interested in sensuality for example the
mind will not think about the ugly
aspects that are simultaneously there
but you can make it do so so that's what
he decided to do there no i will tie you
down this mind and i'll stay
where you told me to go i accept that
that was a good idea thank you
but now we're not changing this i'm
going to stay here until you listen to
me
not other way around
it's not about not having those thoughts
it's not about preventing them from
arriving i shouldn't be thinking this
no it's not up to you what you think
it's up to your mind but you should not
be acting out of it
acting upon it and accepting it without
further consideration
that's on you so
you know exactly where the line is oh
this is not my responsibility mike come
with whatever he wants but i will not
whatever he wants but i will not
entertain it encourage it if it's
unwholesome so to you it's up to you to choose well
so to you it's up to you to choose well
it's up to you to choose
to accept the offer of the mind or not
to go with it along with it to act upon
it or not
and you know it's also it's up to you to
choose whether to
to allow mind to to keep dwelling
and revolt like he needs your input he
needs your encouragement
to keep revolving around say centrality
or something
so you should develop the perception of
danger in those thoughts so while the
mind is thinking
those thoughts of sensuality you are not
wanting them because they are dangerous
not like i will have mind never think
that again
that might be the final outcome of you
being completely dispassionate towards
what your mind presents you with
but until then the mind will be
presenting you with stuff same as any
other sense will be presenting you for
what he wants to do
so you must not welcome it if you know
it
if you see that it's rooted in in
sensuality your will
or distraction
doesn't mean i don't want it let this
let make these thoughts go away no means
i don't want it now i have to endure
this unruly mind that is trying to
harass me with his thoughts
he's saying the other day about
there is a suitor on it that greed
is mildly blameworthy and
slow to fade hatred
is very blameless
delusion is very blameworthy
and slow to sleep it's a delusion is the
the worst it's the subtlest it's the
most um well it's the most primordial out of
um well it's the most primordial out of
three really
so the practice if you you want to
practice getting rid of delusions yeah
well i think what the most or
certainly fairly important thing is to
to make sure that it's not
misunderstood because you know people
like lust is obvious greed is obvious
well obvious obviously on the level of
idea like people you know when you say greed
like people you know when you say greed
people no okay that's greed
but when you say delusion i think more
often than not
people would would think of it as as
like um some sort of confusion ignorance of
um some sort of confusion ignorance of
something you don't know so you're
deluded in some almost like a metaphysical sense
in some almost like a metaphysical sense
and then when you when you become
enlightened now you penetrate it through
the delusion
and you know the secrets have been
revealed and there is no more delusion
in you
so it's not it's not something some some
piece of information that you don't have
it's existential attitude that you have
towards your senses
towards the sense organs the delusion
that's why i often
say delusion slash distraction because
it's it's an
active thing it's not oh yeah delusion
in summer day i'm working through this
method and
techniques and i'm reading the suitors
and you know somehow i'm affecting this
this accumulated delusion at the back of my
accumulated delusion at the back of my
mind no illusion is is something you do
here and now
in the same sense greed is something you
would be doing here and now
or be liable to it and uh anger is
something you'll be doing here and now
or be liable to it that's why it's
greater version delusion
so it's on the same practical basis of
something that you welcome
and act upon and accept and don't see
for what it is
it's not like something you don't know
it's basically something that you keep
doing that is mistaken
towards the senses towards engagement
with the world
the attitude well the attitude of
basically the attitude of distraction
it's about that the the um the movement
of distraction
the the the movement of having something
to do for example
a good indicator as we spoke before
would be to to measure it with
uh boredom if you're easily if somebody
who is easily bored
means you have accumulated a lot of
delusion they will be hard to see and
hard to fade
if you never get bored well you are
probably at least on a gummy or maybe an
arahant but there is no pressure of non-activity
but there is no pressure of non-activity
at all
no pressure to do anything no pressure
to look away or distract yourself from
nothing happening
nothing being felt so practically
speaking boredom is a good good way to practice
boredom is a good good way to practice
as well
and often you know like keeping the
precepts in from your life
that's what's going to result into it
but see then you have the problem of
people don't see
boredom as an indicator and they
certainly don't see a delusion as an
attitude that they still cultivate
despite their commitment to precepts and
commitment to suitors and commitment to
meditation so then they always try to deal with
so then they always try to deal with
border
so even when when they're practicing
your meditation technique
becomes something you do on a kind of
avoiding boredom
you're reading the suitors study
scholarly work becomes something you do
on a kind of avoiding border so
yes you need to know the suttas you need
to collect this information
in order to know what to look for but
sooner or later you need to start
uprooting delusion for what it is
and for that you need to endure and not
depend always on some activity
to keep you occupied and engaged and
basically connected to the senses
say you decide to get bored so switch
your phone off
no no interest in anything close your
doors pull the shutters
it doesn't matter whether you sit stand
walk around your apartment you'll not
obviously watch anything read anything
you will not do your meditation
technique and watch your nostrils and
perform these methods of doing for an
hour you're just going to abide in
you're just going to abide in
non-activity as the suitors would say
so the mind will be presenting you do
this to that
that's fine you don't try to get rid of
those thoughts you just
don't act on it so oh i'll get up okay i
can get up that's not an activity of a
kind that would distract you
i'll go to toilet that's not an activity
of a kind of distract you
oh let me just check my oh that's an
activity of accounts i will not do that
you you probably do that for an hour
you're going to feel intense boredom and
that's why people fear
that solitude confinement when there is
nothing to distract their senses and
give that
impending sort of prospect of doing
something completing something finding
something seeing something hearing
something resolving performing something and
resolving performing something and
that's that's frightening but
in itself being something exactly in
itself that's not frightening
that's only frightening because you've
been depending on the momentum of action
always but that's gratuitous dependence that
but that's gratuitous dependence that
you've been cultivating because
you didn't know any better and for as
long as you don't know any better you
will be cultivating
but so that's when are you delighting in
projects are you delighting in work
means you are delighting in distraction
that's also like where your practice of
samadhi can be
just try and abide in true non-activity
for an hour or two
no meditation techniques no trying to be
mindful performing mindfulness
just sit there don't fall asleep get up
if you're sleepy stand the walk
and then just allow your mind to keep
coming up with these ideas
what to do planning and then don't
commit to them just let them endure
there and
and sit about and do that for three or
four hours
and you see basically there's going to
be space
created unwittingly for most people
initially between you and your senses
because that identification that i
mentioned in the beginning that people
naturally jump into with the senses
sense wants to see i want to see
sense wants to hear i want to hear that
needs maintenance
of that proximity of that closeness of
that immediate acting upon impulse
but if you don't act upon impulse you're
restrained now even your thoughts of hey look at
now even your thoughts of hey look at
this do that plan that
okay let that endure i'm not i'm not
accepting that
i'll probably do it later there's
nothing unwholesome with it but now i'm
concerned about non-activity
you will create that space because you
are not now jumping upon every impulse
of your sense and then you get to
actually see the creature for what it is
the mind there like with thoughts want
to do this want to do that
the monkey mind the you know all the
eyes all these animal comparisons to the
senses you get to see it
because you stop being kind of driven by
them like on a closed leash you actually
like on a closed leash you actually
stepped away
so then even if you choose to do
something say if you establish now that
if that's your practice for most of the
day abiding in non-activity
abiding in non-activity
wakeful because you're not sleeping
obviously and then just
just seeing where your mind comes up
with induce the next thing the next
thing but when you do commit to do something
but when you do commit to do something
with your body with your mouth
with your speech with your mind you do
so only on the level of
that kind of recognition that this will
not cause further distraction
so then those things that you do you do
them through the mind of non-activity
that's why in in ghana you can you know
walk eat go to toilet you know pat your robe
eat go to toilet you know pat your robe
do stuff
it's not like you're frozen motionless
because it's non-activity no
it's what's meant by non-activity means
non uh
not no activity that's rooted in
distraction that it's motivated by that fundamental
that it's motivated by that fundamental
delusion
to distract yourself
so that's that's the measure there and
then it will also become clear what
you're not distracting yourself from
yourself these creatures of the senses
the pressure
that's why people fear boredom oh i'm
bored stay bored a bit longer oh i'm afraid
stay bored a bit longer oh i'm afraid
now
like boredom will always turn into
anxiety you start seeing your existence well you
you start seeing your existence well you
start seeing how basically
divorced from your own senses you are
from the things that you identify with
that that defines what you are is just like
that defines what you are is just like
as i said it's like you know
like somebody releases a helium balloon
that just starts
you know untethered just got higher and
higher and higher and higher that's your mind
and higher and higher that's your mind
now because there is no end to how high
it can go
there's no problem in how high it goes
the problem is from your expectation
and need and dependence of being
tethered to the senses
because you haven't been restraining
yourself enough you haven't been seeing
the danger in the slightest fault
so you have been depending on action of
your senses
and that's that's why like you have men
you know you met
in your life everybody mass people in
life who have
who always depend on having something to
do everybody depends on having something
to do but some people more than
others like when they constantly need to
be active in their interactive
haha border and then restlessness
setting and anxiety and i
and everything doesn't matter how
insignificant becomes the most important
thing in the world it must be done
you know you're dying you're barely
moving you're 90 years old
but your whole life has been depending
on having something to do and you will
still be trying to do stuff because otherwise
be trying to do stuff because otherwise
it's just too frightening
too overwhelming but again
that is just only because you refuse to
give up
the gratuitous assumptions that these
senses are yours
are worth holding on to are the basis
for uh identification because if you
give that up
then the loftiness of non-activity
the expanse the immeasurability of the
non-active mind mind withdrawn from
dependence on the sense activity
is the most sublime thing
but as we described before the pleasure
of jhana
the pleasure of the neutral feeling
needs to be understood
needs to be learned needs to be
developed it's not automatic
and by the way that's why like say
you haven't had anything to do for five
hours you were
confined in a room and then now you're
released and it doesn't matter even the most
and it doesn't matter even the most
dirtiest of the chores you have to go
and clean the toilet you will enjoy it
because at least at least there's
something for you to do
if you're still dependent on the action
and you realize now the pleasure of
having something to do
is determined from how far your mind has
went away
how far has it withdrawn but then you
see people who never experience boredom
because they
always have something lined up to do and
distract themselves with
they are people who then double down
even more onto sensuality
because there's nothing by the way
there's nothing central to cleaning the
toilet and it isn't so you just enjoy the
and it isn't so you just enjoy the
action in itself
because the boredom was a bit too much
to handle
but say you never really experience
boredom you never experience any
separation from the senses like stepping
back no perspective in regard to it
all you do is engage with the senses
that's when you now need even more
engagement for any sense of pleasure and
that's why
the more you engage with sensuality the
less pleasure you feel the more you need to
pleasure you feel the more you need to
engage
let's say you've been withdrawn from
sensuality for a long time even a little
bit of engagement with the sense will be
very agreeable and pleasant
but that doesn't constitute sensuality
engagement with a sense in itself
doesn't constitute sensuality
the further now you have distracted
yourself you use the engagement with the senses
you use the engagement with the senses
basically for the basis of your own
self-delusion from yourself
now you seek the further pleasure of the
sense objects that's where your sensuality
objects that's where your sensuality
sets in that's where the buddha
described the difference between
pleasure that is underlied by
more craving by lust for more pleasure
and pleasure that isn't
so pleasure of cleaning the toilet is
not underlined
for more pleasure to do it it's actually
determined by the fact that you haven't
been engaging with sensuality
and you don't need to feel that pleasure
but you need to be careful though
because you will then be trying to find out
you will then be trying to find out
random things to do
because they are not central but they
can become distracting
and if they do then your mind will start
thinking central thoughts
it goes in that direction exactly goes
further direction and that's why
the same principle taken even further
now say you don't fear the boredom
anymore you don't fear the neutral
feeling it's not felt unpleasantly
because you understood it
you basically live withdrawn from
centrality you have developed the jhana
so your mind is now even more
established upon the greater separation
from the senses and sense pools and so
on
that's why then from that perspective
even enduring this comfort will be
felt like divine pleasure so from point
of view of boredom
cleaning at the toilet will be felt will
be felt extremely
exhilarating from point of view of janna
physical endurance of torture rough road
prepare food will
bear food and and and medicine living on
the root of a tree
will be felt absolutely like the finest
robes the finest food the finest
medicine it's the same principle determined by
it's the same principle determined by
how much your mind is withdrawn
that determines how pleasantly
engagement will be
not in itself that's why for some people
like the whole world of centrality
whatever they want they feel numb
because they've been engaging with that
level of senses for so long mine is not
withdrawn so it's the same principle of withdrawal
so it's the same principle of withdrawal
in bottom if you work through the
boredom donate out of it endure it
even endure that anxiety if it arises um
then even chores will be seen as
agreeable that's fine and you will still not lose
that's fine and you will still not lose
not unless you choose to you will not
lose the that recognition that
oh the non-activity state of mind that
has arisen on account of enduring
boredom and not acting upon the sense
well see because of that i have pleasant
abiding here and now when i do have to
engage with the senses
now you develop that further into a
genre now even if you don't do any chores just
now even if you don't do any chores just
just enduring the elements
will be agreeable will be seen
pleasantly from the point of view of
mind so withdrawn
and that's what it would have encouraged
venerable said practice jhana
so that the rough robes you wear will
feel like silk
because of the mind of jhana mind of
withdrawal from the senses
so that's what i mean you don't need to
fear oh but so me enjoying these rough
robes oh that sensuality that's only person
oh that sensuality that's only person
who is not free from centrality would
use that as a ref and think that
everything is centrality
because that's the only reference you
have and even the buddha himself
initially thought
the pleasure of that withdrawal
is unwholesome but it says wait why do i
fear this pleasure
that is not connected with that double
down pleasure of sense objects that you
have to be craving for more if you
engage with
it's always underlied by by more oh this
is not underlined so why do i fear it
what if i don't fear it
and then he realized it shouldn't be
feared so if you're enjoying
the living in the in the in the jungle
wearing the rough robes and enduring
insects if you find that
agreeable you don't need to hold that
centrality because it isn't
that agreeability of it is determined by
your state of
loftiness of your mind so you're not
distracting yourself
you will inevitably find things
enjoyable if you develop genres as they
did in the suttas even like the the
extreme physical rotting guts and stuff like no
physical rotting guts and stuff like no
that's all right i didn't do this no
problem because my mind can obtain jhanas it
because my mind can obtain jhanas it
will in other words my mind can
reestablish itself as fully withdrawn
and independent of
any sense at will how can i be bothered
by anything that comes through any sense
when mahathir was offered by the buddha
because he was already old
to leave the raf forest stop living
keeping all those dutanga ascetic
practices because it's it's too much and
the will said
you did your work there's really no need
for this come on i get plenty of ropes
plenty of food plenty of lodging i'll
pass it down unto you
there's really no need for you to
torture yourself he says oh no lord this
is not a torture
whoever can obtain janna's at will this
is what they want to do this is where
their joy is
and then it was oh you're truly
practicing for the sake of future
generation in other words that's the
inspiring thing to do you don't need to
do it there is no further dhamma to be
developed you completed everything
now you do it for the sake of pleasure
and joy that you find in it because
you can obtain john as it will
and he you know there were no records of
him how he died but he must have died in
the same environment
he never left the hardship and ascetic
practices because they were not
the relativity of hardship and endurance
determined by how much your mind is
withdrawn from these things or not
and that is that's why it's not
incidental that boredom is always that
fundamental thing that nobody wants to
deal with
even people that practice the dharma the
practice of dhamma because something you
do
to avoid that sinking into that border
so yeah say you've been sitting for
three hours closing your room
everything's switched off no
notifications no activity and you want
to get up and drink tea
fine now your mind start wants to
overthink it
wants to get into details that's what
you don't welcome doesn't mean i will
never drink tea again
and it but you see that you will not
exactly you will not lose the sight of
yourself which means
even making of the tea will not become a
basis for that self-deluding
whereby you become unaware of yourself
and you fall into the identification of
the senses you're engaging with
you still maintain that that distance
the right perspective
if you are living in such a way
non-distraction doing things
not to distract yourself your life
becomes simple naturally sure
naturally resulting
the amount of proliferation and
elaboration there was the census and
engagement with it
yeah they will have to diminish they
would fail
that's why working talking and sleeping
not central in itself
can be a basis for slowing down
the uh the sotafana's progress it's
mentioned in the sutures
so the one with the right view who if he
were to practice sense restraint and
learn to abide in non-activity even more
will become an arahant in this life
but then they get distracted with work
talk and sleep that becomes basically
obstruction to their own progress
that's where the buddha would tell off
and under another you know marias
they were like busy sewing robes and
stuff it was obviously not necessary to
the extent that they were doing
and they would have really rebuked them
it's not central enjoying work is not
essential enjoying talk is not central unless
enjoying talk is not central unless
obviously the talk is about centrality
if you lose the context and if you if
you don't
maintain that transparency in regard to
the motivation behind engagement with
work talk and sleep it will become a basis
talk and sleep it will become a basis
for for maintaining
obviously for you know for an aria he
maintains that delusion much subtler
than a pathogen would be doing but he's still
a pathogen would be doing but he's still
a form of
that self-destruction and all will he
need to all he would need to do is not
not engage
or not allow himself to be engaged with
work for the purpose of distraction
talk for the purpose of distraction and
sleep for the purpose of distraction
and he will progress towards nibana no
other effort he needs to make
because he already understood the effort
of non-activity well exactly it's the
effort of protecting the mind of
non-activity that's all we understood is what you do
that's all we understood is what you do
abiding on activity as a pleasant
abiding here and now
paired with your right view is basically
ghana that leads you to nibbana
but as i said many times john is not a
product of your activity john is the product of
of your activity john is the product of
withdrawal from the senses
pleasure and security that comes from it
so the true non-activity
but again non-activity is basically
whether you're
motivated by distraction or not it's not
whether you are motionless or not
so you might just jump into a conclusion
and non-activity means motionless for
three hours i will refuse to move
because there will be a distraction of
activity no
non-activity means non-distraction so
you abiding in non-distraction and you
know that by the way
just as i said just sit in a flat and
see within five minutes the mind will
present you something to do and
do you you will catch yourself are you
relishing the idea of
yes let me do this let me click that
button let me open that door let me look
at this
if if so there you go that is the
activity that is the distraction not acting upon
that is the distraction not acting upon
an impulse to act
it's already creating some space between
you and your senses
that's why none of this will be possible
unless you
keep the precepts beforehand and
practice and restrain your senses
non-activities not being motivated
you're not using any type of action
for the means of distraction of yourself
from yourself
so not use any type of action
for the basis for identification with
the census for losing the perspective of
the creature that needs to be contained
and restrained and kept
an eye on and there's nothing like
the decrease of delusion and the right
perspective they're keeping it that perspective
they're keeping it that perspective
oh yeah sure sure sure increase yeah but
if you start giving in to these
distracting activities the perspective
the right perspective will diminish
or will be more obscured
if you don't give in to these acts of
self-distraction the perspective is maintained so you
the perspective is maintained so you
don't need to i must keep this
perspective all i need to do is protect
it by not distracting myself
from it indirect so once you stop
being engaged with the world like with
work or whatever else you have to do
now you realize oh there is enough space
for me here to see
if the actions i'm about to do and what
i'm doing when i'm not working
do i need to and to what extent i'm
using that for basically pleasure of
of kind of indolence and forgetting
about this creature that i do need to keep an
this creature that i do need to keep an
eye on
you don't eat as i said before you need
to be choking creature and constantly
tying it up
but you do need to not lose the sight of
it
so now that you've finished your work
when you come back at home you need to
rest does that include binge watching
does that include binge watching
i don't know a four hour long movie
having a drink
listening to the music where does it
where does it say that you need to do
that for relaxation all you need to do
is for relaxation is not do any work
so you just okay yeah so i i can easily
relax myself and enjoy doing nothing
or enjoy doing something that's
non-distracting and they will not result
in me wanting to do more of it and
losing the sight of myself
but i could then also choose to do
things that would result in such things
so
watching entertainment engagement
with chit chat people company or that
will take you away even further from the
mind so although it's
not technically still central it's
already heading in that direction
the direction of depending on activity
and work and so on which means
it's just a question of time when you're
going to be seeking the central objects
and so on
so that's what i mean you you want to
relax but not to the point of losing the
sight of the creature you need to keep an eye
of the creature you need to keep an eye
on that you are
and often people conflate the two i've
done my work
now i can relax means i can lose the
sight no
yes you can relax but at no point
that means you are allowed to lose the
sight of the creature of the six senses
that's that's a no-no so that's that
difference between
activity and non-activity if you don't
lose the sight of the creature you will
not be active on the level of the
creature even if you're doing the chores you will
even if you're doing the chores you will
be doing them through the mind of
non-activity only to the minimum point of complete
only to the minimum point of complete
the need
the purpose and then you're back into
non-activity and abiding in ghana
basically it seems like eating if you want to eat
it seems like eating if you want to eat
same with eating exactly to the extent
that needs to be eaten
then finished then not seen is even
pleasurable to do more
what is pleasurable is protecting the
mind that makes everything else
pleasurable from that
high stance it is uh that's the true
pleasure that's the pleasure that's not
that's the pleasure that's not
underlined by craving for more and that
pleasure is not unwholesome
it's safe and you're mindful in it so
it's a win-win